Hello, and welcome back to
another episode with ItsDrDan.
And today we're going to be learning how
to count valence electrons and draw Lewis
structures for atoms, cations, and anions.
So we're looking, we're not going to be
looking at the bonding picture, but just
how, how do you do the basics, right?
How to stick to your fundamentals.
So let's just get into it.
So the first thing is, let's say if
I have nitrogen, which if you kind of
remember from your chemistry class,
well, that has an atomic number of seven.
So if you kind of remember,
well, what is an atom?
Atoms are inherently neutral, meaning
they have set, they have the same
number of protons as they do electrons.
So for, for something like nitrogen,
well, if it has seven protons,
being that we have our number here,
then it also has seven electrons.
And when you were starting that
off, when you first learned about
electrons, typically we learned how
to organize it via the Bohr model.
Which if you remember, well, that
first, that first level, that, or that
shell, it will have two electrons.
And then the next shell is going
to have the other five electrons.
evenly spread out.
So we have 1,2, 3, 4 and 5 all spread out.
Now, what do all of these represent?
Well, we have our different levels.
Well, the ones that we are interested
in today are the outermost level.
These are referred to as
the valence electrons.
So it's your outer shell.
So one way to look at this, this atom is
like, it's like layers of an onion, right?
You can peel off those individual layers.
Well, what layer do you peel first?
Well, it's the outermost.
So when it comes to cations
and anions, well, that's what's
going to be behaving in all this
chemistry are those outer levels.
Now, you might also have to
label what the inner levels are.
These are referred to as the
core electrons, which are so
close to the nucleus, right?
The center of the atom that typically
they don't behave in chemistry,
in that many chemical reactions.
So the valence level is
what we're going to look at.
So we're going to learn some methods
on how to count them, some simple
ones, so that we just using your
periodic table, what you are given
on an exam or on a homework for
most of your chemistry classes.
And then we'll go through different
ways to draw Lewis dot structures.
Let's get at some different examples.
Now, the easiest method for being able
to count valence electrons is by using
your periodic table and marking the
columns found on the periodic table.
So if we get, if we look at this and
we look at the first column, what
we're going to do is we're going
to just label it like how you would
number any column that you would see,
which would be with the number 1.
So when we do that, we label
the first one as number one, the
second column with number two.
And what those represent is the
number of valence electrons for all
of the elements in that particular
group or family, or also column.
So for example, hydrogen, lithium,
and sodium, they all have one valence
electron in their outermost layer.
Right.
So if you're kind of just to show
those as quick examples, right, if
you think of hydrogen, well, it has
an electron configuration of 1s1,
meaning that it has one electron in
its outermost level, which is one.
If you think of lithium, well,
that one is 1s1, or sorry, 1s2.
And then 2s1.
Notice once again, we have one
electron in each of those levels.
And then if we go down to sodium, and
I do the same thing where I write down
its electron configuration, well, notice
we have the same trend where we have
one electron in its outermost layer,
which is that highest number, right?
So 1, 2, 3, those are the highest numbers.
The second, second column, right, where
Beryllium and Magnesium are, we can also
put Helium in that position as well.
So Helium, even though it is a noble
gas and it's on the far right hand
side of the periodic table, we can
pretend that Helium is located here
for valence electron purposes, being
that Helium also has two electrons.
So then as we kind of go through
that periodic table, right, we can
fill in the rest of the columns.
We can pretty much kind of move this
for now, where we can say like, okay,
let's kind of get rid of helium for
at the moment, where it's going to be
on that far side, gone away, right?
And we're going to put, okay, so now
that we have those different numbers,
These represent the number of valence
electrons in their outermost layer.
Let's practice drawing these as
Lewis structures for many of these
examples that we have listed above.
Alright, so our first example of
going through how to draw different
Lewis dot structures for atoms.
So let's just go through our
periodic table, practicing
counting valence electrons.
So if we start with the first
one, which is hydrogen, right?
Hydrogen is all the way up here on that
top left side of the periodic table.
So, and that belongs in
the S orbital, right?
So that's its highest level.
So I wrote down all the electron
configurations for these elements
for us because we just want to
focus on how to write the notation.
So if I have hydrogen, 1s1, we
can see that, well, that is its
outermost level is this 1s1 area.
Now, same thing with Helium, right?
1s2, that is its highest level.
So what we're going to do is we're
going to draw the atom first of
Hydrogen, and we're going to use a
dot to represent its valence electron.
So being that this one has one
single valence electron, we'll
just write that as H with a dot.
And it doesn't matter exactly where you
put that dot, you can put it on the top.
You can put it on the left,
you can put it on the bottom.
They all represent that we have one
valence electron around our hydrogen.
And this is going to be important for
when you get into covalent bonding,
all about how we can make bonds to
share electrons, which will help you
be able to illustrate that, which
there are other videos on my channel as
well to help go into covalent bonding.
Now, with Helium, Helium is the same
idea, so what we're going to be doing
this time as well, we have a complete
orbital for Helium, meaning we have two
electrons, it has a complete level, right?
Remember this, even though I wrote it in
little dashed lines up here, this is like
a noble, this is a noble guess, right?
Meaning that it is happy, it's
fulfilling what we refer to as happiness.
for this one is the duet rule, right?
It is, has a complete level.
Um, so for this one, it's going to be
a little different than all the others.
We're going to put those two
dots together to help represent.
that this has a complete orbital.
And we can put them like I did
before, is on any side, as long as
you have some kind of consistency
with the way you write these.
Now, so that's hydrogen and helium, right?
We have two valence electrons.
Two dots.
So we have one valence electron, right?
Two valence electrons.
And that's going off the
columns of our periodic table.
So one and two.
Um, and just to kind of
help illustrate that, right?
One, one and two here.
So our next one, right, is
going to be boron and aluminum.
So if I have, uh, sorry.
All right, I go to the next one.
So if I go down to lithium, right?
Lithium and beryllium.
So lithium is right below hydrogen.
So how many valence
electrons should I have?
Well, based on our trend here, it
should also have one, but I thought
that lithium has three electrons.
How is that the case?
Well, what we're going to be doing
is counting its highest level.
So when you are looking at your
periodic table, right, we can see
that lithium is right here, right?
It falls under column number one.
So what we can do is, is by seeing that we
know it has one valence electron, whether
we have the electron configuration or not.
One thing to keep in mind is, well, being
that we do, the electron configuration,
all's we are doing is counting S and
P Electrons in the highest level.
That is it.
So we only count s and p, right?
So I'm going to write that down here
because it's really important to see.
Only count S and P and
that has to be the highest.
Okay.
So, so keep that in mind.
So that's all we're going to be counting.
So with lithium, right, what we
can see the highest one is 2S1.
So once again, we have that
one feature here as our answer.
So one balanced electron.
And it is going to also
be just one single dot.
So let's do this one in a different color.
So lithium has just one dot.
And as before, it doesn't
matter where you put it.
Let's go on to the next.
Well, the next one, brilliant, right?
Once again, we can see
our highest level is 2s2.
How many do we have here?
Well, now we have two valence
electrons in that highest orbital.
So now we can do is
write two dots this time.
So we do, um, beryllium
and we write one, two.
And notice the difference between
beryllium and helium, right?
Helium has a complete level.
So we write them together.
However, beryllium does not.
It still has room to grow.
And that's because we now have
access to the, the p electrons.
So when you go down to boron, notice how
in the second level, We have p electrons.
So, we don't have 2 anymore, but we
have 3 valence electrons because we're
moving down our periodic table, right?
1, 2, 3.
The boron now has those three.
So, and as we keep growing, we can kind
of make some predictions here, right?
Is that, well, when we go to carbon,
well, that's going to be four valence
electrons, and we can show this, right?
The whole idea is that as we grow, we're
going to keep putting dots on every side.
So, with boron, we'll do one, two, three.
With carbon, we'll do
one, two, three, four.
And the way we're drawing these is imagine
that our element is in a little box that
we're filling the dots around each side.
Now what happens when we
go over, go over four?
Well, if we go to nitrogen, which is now
five valence electrons, and the way to
kind of highlight that, just to keep that
highlighting up, right, so boron was these
two, carbon was, uh, these two here, oops,
and then nitrogen was these five, right?
So we're adding up the superscripts.
So for nitrogen, two plus three is five.
So when we are doing this, we are
going to have, write our nitrogen, and
then we are going to put a dot on each
side, right, 4, and then we're going
to double up our dots on another side.
It does not matter where
the double up is happening.
Personally, I prefer the top.
That's what most people do when
they are drawing this, right?
So you can either draw it like
that, or if you want to, you
can write dot, dot, dot, dot.
And maybe you have them
both on the right hand side.
There is no particular method as
long as you are being consistent.
Um, you will hear some
different professors.
They'll tell you like, oh, it
has to be top down, left, right.
It does not.
Um, with oxygen, all right, same
idea here, right, we're going to go
down that, we're going to highlight
our valence electrons, so 2 plus
4, which means 6 valence electrons.
Notice how that's also matching
up with our column, right, so
oxygen's here in the 6th one.
You see Fluorine is 7, Neon
is 8, so we can keep building
this, but why don't we do that?
So we'll see that, okay, Oxygen
is 6, Fluorine is 7, and then
8, and then we can write all of
those little pieces for ourselves.
So Oxygen, so Oxygen, we
will do 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
Fluorine will do 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, and
then Neon, which is our last one, we will
do 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, and 8, right?
So we're filling in all those
sides all around our species.
And this is how we do Lewis dot
structures for just a normal atom.
Remember, the goal for all
these different elements is to
get towards our noble gases.
Right, so either we want to achieve
the octet rule, Or, we want to achieve
the duet rule for hydrogen, helium,
lithium, beryllium around that area.
We want to be a noble gas.
So let's look at how to do
this for cations and anions
and look at the difference.
Alright, so our last example is
talking all about cations and anions.
And if you remember from my
previous videos talking about
ionic species, that was when we
were gaining and losing electrons.
So, to remember that, losing an
electron was all about being a cation,
so meaning when you lose an electron,
you are more positive, so cations
are positive, so if you remember a
cat, right, has paws, it is positive.
So an anion is negative, think of
that negative thing where onions make
you cry, that'll help you remember
that onions are more negative,
meaning more electrons, right, it's
all about a balance of charges.
So how do we do this when it
comes to Lewis dot structures?
Let's do our, let's do an easy.
Let's do a simple one.
Let's say if I have hydrogen, hydrogen has
one dot, meaning that it has one s one.
Well, hydrogen, what is the predictable
charge of hydrogen well being?
It's in that first column.
It has a predictable
charge of plus one, right?
So everything in that column would
be a plus one, this is plus two.
Why don't we just fill in the
rest of our charges as well?
So let's say if I, I'll do negative
one, negative two, negative three,
for our predictable charges.
So hydrogen, it is prone
to giving up an electron.
So where is that going to come from?
Well, it's going to come from our
valence level, our outermost shell.
So when that happens, well, let's
say if we have H and it loses its
electron, we will put that in brackets
to denote that it lost its electron,
and then we'll put a positive symbol.
Notice how it doesn't have a dot anymore.
It lost its electron.
Now let's try a different one.
What if instead I do,  we'll
do,  oxygen, for example.
So if I have oxygen, well,
oxygen has how many dots?
Well, if we go to our periodic table,
we can double check that for ourselves.
We can see that oxygen is at six, so
it should have six dots all around it.
So when we go about and try to write
that for ourselves, we're going
to fill in all those little dots.
So we have 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, right?
So six valence electrons.
Now if we want to draw,
let's say O two minus, right?
Well, what is the difference?
Well, O2- means that it
gained two electrons.
So it has more electrons.
This is an anion versus
H which was a cation.
So when we are an anion, what we now
need to do is not only do we want to
show the six dots we had before, But we
are going to be adding two dots as well.
So we'll represent that in orange.
Now when we have those extra
two dots, notice how the octet
rule is satisfied, right?
We have all eight of them.
And we can put here that two negative to
tell you, hey, this is an ion that has
extra electrons that are here, and this
is gonna be really important when you
have to do ionic bonding Lewis structures
and potentially covalent as well.
It'll help guide you in seeing
how many bonds these can do.
Let's try another.
So let's say if I had a sodium,
sodium has one valence electron.
Now if I want to do sodium
plus, Well, how would I do that?
Well, it would be just like so.
You'd put it in brackets
and put a plus sign.
Now, depending on where you are learning
chemistry, you can potentially show
that, um, what is its new valence level.
Well, let's write it out.
So, sodium neutral has
1s2, 2s2, 2p6, 3s1, right?
And we removed, we're going to
be removing this outermost level.
So sodium plus on the other
hand, well, it just has the same
configuration as neon, right?
So when I take this, it has
the following configuration.
So can you write it where we
have eight valence electrons?
Well, you can, you can show that,
okay, this has eight valence
electrons all around it, as long as.
You illustrate that it has a positive
around it to tell you, Hey, this is
missing, this missing one electron.
It has this complete octet, so
you can show either or most of
the time though, this is the
preferred and more common method.
However, every class is a little
bit different, which have different
purposes, so keep that in mind.
If you're not sure, you can
always ask your professor or your
teacher which one they prefer.
But I know with my students, typically
I'm more in favor of this one, but I
know every class is a little different.
So keep that in mind, right?
Little warning.
Anything you see on YouTube,
you want to make sure you double
check with your professor.
So that is another example of a cation.
Let's do one more.
So what if I have, let's say nitrogen?
Well, nitrogen, let's check how
many valence electrons this has.
We can go to our periodic table.
We can see that it is on column
number five here, so it is right
here, uh, where we see n, n seven,
that tells you seven protons, seven
electrons, five of which are valence.
So let's kind of talk
about that for a second.
So we have seven total electrons.
Five are valence electrons.
What about the other two?
What are they?
Well, that means that there
are two, four electrons, right?
So all these added together is going to
be making your total number of electrons.
So keep that in mind.
That all the, the core and valence added
together equals your total electrons.
So sometimes you might have a class that
requires you to  show both those sides.
So now that we have our nitrogen
here, we're going to write our dots.
So we had five, right?
One, two, three, four, five.
Now, let's try the anion form, right?
If I tell you N3 minus, well, how
is that going to be changing things?
Well being that this is one S two two
S, two two P three, the N three minus
is gonna be one SS two, two S two,
and this is going to be two P six.
That's our change, right?
So notice that that number goes
up three because we are an anion.
So when we draw our Lewis dot structure,
we'll write one, two, three, four,
five, and then we'll put our last,
our two, our three new dots as a,
um, to show that this is an anion.
And then we would write in
brackets with a three minus.
This is how you can write Lewis dot
structures for atoms, cations, and anions.
I didn't see a lot of videos like
this on YouTube, and I thought,
let's just go over the basics.
If you would like to go over covalent
and molecular bonded, uh, bonds,
go to my follow up video on this
on how to draw Lewis structures.
It's a little bit of an older video for
now, but hopefully that can help you be
able to understand these little basics.
This is Dr.
Dan, and I hope to see you all in
the future, and I hope this helps.
Thank you all for liking and subscribing,
and I hope to see you all in the future.
Bye now!